Have you ever wondered
if there are more natural ways
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the best
way to treat a condition
that affects nearly
60 percent of all women.
DHEA supplements
don’t seem to help
with female sexual dysfunction,
but what about
other dietary supplements,
such as the three roots:
ginseng, maca, and ashwagandha?
Ginseng has been suggested,
given its demonstrated efficacy
for male erectile dysfunction
and the fact that it causes
a relaxation response in vitro
to isolated strips
of rabbit vaginal tissue.
But when put to the test
in human studies,
a meta-analysis found
no statistically significant
effect of ginseng
on female sexual dysfunction.
Maca root has been advertised
as Peruvian Viagra.
It’s an important dietary staple
of the indigenous people
of Peru
but appears
to have been overly hyped
as a libido enhancer
based largely on studies
of male rodents.
Yes, maca seems to enhance
the sexual function
of male mice and rats,
but of the two trials
on sexual desire in male humans,
only one showed
a significant benefit,
but it took eight weeks
to show an effect,
which may explain
the negative results
of the second study,
which only lasted two weeks.
A pilot study
without a placebo control
on the management
of sexual dysfunction
induced by SSRIs (due to drugs
like Prozac or Zoloft)
on mostly women
suggested maca may be useful,
but when properly put
to the test in a randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial,
it failed to have
a significant effect.
The necessity of placebos
is illustrated
by a maca trial
for infertility.
Maca increased
sperm concentration
by 40 percent!
Yeah, but the placebo
in the study
improved sperm concentration
by 76 percent,
so maca didn’t work after all.
Having placebo controls
is particularly important
for female sexual dysfunction,
since based on studies
of almost 4,000 women,
the placebo effect accounts
for more than two-thirds
of the treatment effect,
similar to the placebo efficacy
of antidepressants.
In contrast, improvement rates
for erectile dysfunction
in men given placebos
are on the order
of 15 percent or less.
The thought is that just the act
of consistent self-monitoring
in female sexual dysfunction
trials,
for example by being asked
to keep a symptom diary,
may improve symptoms
by heightening
the participant’s attention
and awareness
of her own responses
and behaviors,
even in lieu
of an active treatment.
There was one small randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled trial of maca
for sexual dysfunction
in postmenopausal women.
Fourteen women
were randomized
to about 3/4 of a teaspoon
(~4 g) of maca powder
or a placebo powder
every day for six weeks,
after which point they switched
for another six weeks.
While on the real maca,
they reported
significantly fewer symptoms
of sexual dysfunction.
Ashwagandha is a revered herb
of the traditional Indian
Ayurvedic system of medicine.
Its name comes from "ashwa,"
which means horse,
and "gandha,"
which means smell,
because the roots
evidently possess
the "distinctive smell
of a wet horse."
Ashwagandha is used
as a household remedy in India
where it’s been considered
a rasayana, a "rejuvenator,"
or "tonic,"
for thousands of years,
earning it the nickname
of Indian ginseng.
After being fed the root,
rodents thrown
into the deep end
swim twice as long
before sinking
(12 hours versus 6 hours).
Benefits for
physical performance
(including an increase
in aerobic fitness)
have been found in people too.
One study demonstrated evidence
of cognitive benefits as well.
Its Latin name,
Withania somnifera
points to another use
(somnifera means
"sleep-inducer").
A meta-analysis of five
randomized controlled trials
of ashwagandha extracts
found a small
but significant effect
on overall sleep.
What about ashwagandha
and female sexual dysfunction?
Women ages 21 thorough 50
were randomized
to two months
of the estimated equivalent
of three grams
of ashwagandha root powder
and did not have
an increase in sexual desire,
but they did show improvements
over placebo in arousal,
lubrication, orgasm,
and satisfaction,
translating into an additional
quote-unquote
"successful sexual encounter"
by the end of the study.
What are the downsides?
Ashwagandha belongs
to the nightshade family,
which includes some
shady characters like tobacco
and, well,
deadly nightshade.
There have been rare cases
of ashwagandha-linked
liver toxicity reported,
though commercial
herbal supplements
are often mislabeled,
so it’s hard to definitively
attribute certain cases.
However, there have been
several liver injury cases
in which the supplements
have been tested
and found to be
contaminant-free,
suggesting that ashwagandha-
induced liver toxicity
is a real phenomenon,
however rare.
What should we expect
from a plant
known by its other nickname,
poison gooseberry.
Did you know that the buildup
of cholesterol in pelvic arteries
can lead to sexual problems
among both men and women
via a similar pathway?
Here’s the story.
Cholesterol doesn’t just build up
inside our coronary arteries;
it builds up inside
all of our arteries.
In the heart,
it can cause a heart attack.
In the brain,
it can cause a stroke.
In our legs, it can cause
peripheral vascular disease.
And clogs in our pelvic arteries
can lead to sexual dysfunction—
and not just in men.
“Hyperlipidemia and sexual function
in premenopausal women.”
Those with high cholesterol “reported
significantly lower arousal, orgasm,
lubrication, and satisfaction.
Atherosclerosis of the arterial bed
supplying female pelvic anatomy
can lead to decreased vaginal engorgement
and clitoral erectile
insufficiency syndrome,
similar to erectile problems in men,
resulting in vasculogenic
female sexual dysfunction,”
an important factor of which may be
failure to achieve “clitoral tumescence,”
or engorgement.
Eating healthier can extend one’s life
and also one’s love life.
In our final story today,
we look at dietary approaches
to female sexual dysfunction.
The creation and promotion of
“female sexual dysfunction”
as a mental disorder seems
like a textbook case of disease-mongering
by the pharmaceutical industry harkening
back to the first DSM,
psychiatry’s diagnosis manual,
which listed frigidity as a mental disorder,
along, of course, with homosexuality.
The latest manifestation is hypoactive
sexual desire disorder,
a disease invented by drug companies.
It’s like when Prozac was
about to go off patent,
the company sponsored the creation
of new mental illness to market
a drug called Sarafem,
which was simply Prozac repacked
into a pink capsule.
The condition previously known
as shyness was branded as
“social anxiety disorder;”
so they could get kids on Paxil.
There are certainly women
who are troubled by low libido,
but there is no reliable
scientific evidence that
hypoactive sexual desire disorder
is a real medical condition.
And, women can get
diagnosed with it
even with a normal libido.
A woman highly interested in sex,
just not (for whatever reason)
with her current partner,
can still qualify for the
diagnosis—and the drug.
Even a woman who is perfectly satisfied
with her sex life may still
qualify if her partner isn’t.
Our story begins in 2009,
when a drug company tried
to get a failed antidepressant
called Flibanserin approved
to treat hypoactive sexual desire disorder.
The only problem...?
It didn’t work.
It was resubmitted again after more study,
and was still rejected, as was the appeal.
But, in 2015, the FDA approved the drug.
What changed?
Nothing about its efficacy;
it didn’t work any better.
What changed is that the drug company
that bought it helped launch
an astroturf fake grassroots
advocacy group,
“Even the Score,” which lobbied
for approval under a feminist rubric.
Men have their drugs;
why don’t women get any sex drugs,
which was exposed as
kind of a bitter irony.
But hey, within 48 hours of FDA approval,
the drug was sold for
a cool billion in cash.
Very satisfying for the drug company,
but what about the women
who take the drug
(now sold as Addyi)?
Not much.
The drug just doesn’t work as advertised.
Yes, it may stimulate monkeys
to groom each other more.
But, when researchers dug up
the unpublished data about the drug,
any clinical benefit was found
to be marginal,
and the drug was found to have
significant adverse side effects.
Besides being ineffective,
it can be dangerous.
Combining it with alcohol can cause
dangerous hypotension and fainting—
problems so serious that the FDA
put a black box warning on it,
its most serious safety alert,
on the label (that of course no one reads).
Even without alcohol,
it can cause severe drops
in blood pressure levels and cause
sudden prolonged unconsciousness.
Now, serious side effects
might be acceptable
in some kind of cancer
wonder drug or something,
but are entirely unacceptable in a drug
given to healthy women
for an invented condition.
Are there any safe and natural solutions?
Well, there’s lots of studies
on diet and men’s sexual health,
but what about women’s?
I’ve previously explored the evidence
about women with high cholesterol levels
reporting diminished sexual function
across a number of dimensions.
This could explain why a
more plant-based diet,
rich in a variety of whole plant foods,
might be effective in ameliorating
sexual function issues in women,
as it does in men,
more whole grains, beans,
vegetables, and fruit,
and less meat, dairy, and sugar
associated with a reduced risk
of erectile dysfunction,
because the anatomy and physiology
of sexual responses are actually
quite similar between the two;
they can have a similar effect.
You can measure clitoral engorgement
with fancy MRI techniques within
minutes of exposure to an erotic video.
And, we know now that lubrication
is all about blood flow too.
Within the sexually aroused vagina,
it’s the hydrostatic pressure
from all the additional pelvic
blood flow that forces fluid
to leak out onto the surface
as the vaginal lubrication.
So, how can we improve blood flow?
Well, the flavonoid phytonutrients
in cocoa can help open up arteries,
increasing pulse wave amplitude
peaking at about 90
minutes after consumption.
So, can that Valentine’s Day chocolate
make a difference?
Women who eat chocolate do tend
to have higher female sexual
function index scores,
but the effect disappeared once
age was taken into account.
So, despite all the potential biological
mechanisms supporting a role
for chocolate as an aphrodisiac food,
the study failed to show a benefit.
One would assume that chocolate
could improve blood flow,
but remember that was with cocoa powder.
Maybe the fat and sugar in chocolate
is counteracting the benefits.
What are some whole food
sources of flavonoids?
Well, onions have a lot.
And indeed, fresh onion juice enhances
copulatory behavior—in rats,
but for those of us less interested
in increasing the percentage
of ejaculating rats,
and looking for something other
than onion juice for our hot date,
how about that apple?
There wasn’t a study addressing
the potential correlation between
daily apple consumption and
women’s sexual function…
until now.
The title kind of gives it away,
but women were split into
regular daily apple consumers
versus those consuming less
than an apple a day,
and the hundreds of apple eaters
in the study scored significantly
higher on the female
sexual function index.
Now, note they only included women
eating unpeeled apples,
because the phytonutrients are
concentrated in the peel:
so, we don’t know if there’s a link
with peeled apples.
And, this was just an observational study;
so, further studies will be necessary
to clarify the relationship
between apple intake and female sexuality.
However, the present data can allow
the “development of future research
for identifying new compounds
and food supplements to use
in female sexuality recovery.”
Uh, or, you can just try
eating an apple.
Visit nutritionfacts.org/audio to see
all of the podcast episodes
with descriptions that include
links to their associated videos.
Sources cited and other details are
available on each video's page.
Information about my books—
How Not to Die, How Not to Diet,
and How Not to Age—
is at nutritionfacts.org/books.
All proceeds from book
sales go to charity.
And sign up for our free newsletter
at nutritionfacts.org/subscribe
to stay updated on the latest
bite-sized videos and articles.
NutritionFacts.org is a
science-based non-profit,
and everything on
the website is free.
There are no ads, no corporate
sponsorships, no kickbacks.
Strictly non-commercial,
not selling anything.
I just put up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.
Thanks for listening.